片名： 人格面具 (假面)
导演：英格玛．伯格曼
主演：比比．安德森
主演：莉芙．厄尔曼
你找我吗?医生
You wanted to talk with me, doctor?
你见过沃哥夫人了吗,艾玛护士?
Have you been to see Mrs. Vogler yet, Sister Alma?
没,现在还没有
No, not yet.
我给你解释一下她的情况
Let me explain her situation
以及为什么让你来照顾她的原因
and the reason why you have been hired to care for her.
正如你知道的,沃哥夫人是一名演员
Mrs. Vogler is an actress, as you know.
在她的最后一场演出《恋父》中
During her last performance of Electra,
她突然就不说话了,并很惊讶地看周围的情况
she fell silent and looked around as if in surprise.
她这样沉默了一分多钟
She was silent for over a minute.
之后她道歉了,并说她很想笑
She apologized afterward, saying she had got the urge to laugh.
第二天剧院上班的时候
The next day the theater rang,
沃哥夫人没有赶去排演
as Mrs. Vogler had not come to rehearsals.
仆人发现她仍然躺在床上
The maid found her still in bed.
她已经醒了,但不搭理女仆也不动
She was awake but did not talk or move.
这种情况到目前为止已经有三个月了
This condition has now lasted for three months.
她已经做了各种检查
She has had all sorts of tests.
心智上和身体上都很正常
She's healthy both mentally and physically.
甚至没有一点异常反应
It's not even some kind of hysterical reaction.
有什么疑问吗,艾玛护士?
Any questions, Sister Alma?
那好,你可以去沃哥夫人那里了
Well, then, you can go to Mrs. Vogler now.
你好,沃哥夫人
How do you do, Mrs. Vogler?
我是艾玛护士
I am Sister Alma.
是来照顾你的
I'm here to take care of you.
或许我该向你介绍一下我自己
Maybe I should tell you a little about myself.
我今年25岁,已经订婚了
I'm 25 years old and engaged.
两年前取得护士资格征
I graduated from nursing school two years ago.
我父母在乡下有一个农场
My parents have a farm in the country.
我母亲在结婚之前也是个护士
My mother was also a nurse until she got married.
我该为你拿晚餐了
I should go get your dinner tray.
炸猪肝和水果色拉
Fried liver and fruit salad.
看起来很美味
It looked tasty.
要加个枕头吗?这样行吗?
Another pillow? Is that good?
艾玛护士,你的第一印象如何?
Sister Alma, what's your first impression?
我不知该怎么说,医生
I don't know what to say, doctor.
她的脸看起来很温和,还带点孩子气
Her face looks soft, almost childish.
但她的眼神……
Then you see her eyes...
有种让人不舒服的表情
She has a mean look, I think.
我不知道．我不应该……  你想说什么?
- I don't know. I shouldn't... - What were you going to say?
我在想是否该负责照顾这个病人
I thought I should say no to this case.
为什么?害怕了?
Why? Did something frighten you?
不,没有
No, not exactly.
可能沃哥夫人需要更年长的人
Perhaps Mrs. Vogler needs an older person
生活经验更丰富的
with more life experience.
我可能应付不了她……  应付?在什么方面?
- I might not be able to handle her. - Handle? In what way?
精神方面  精神方面?
- Mentally. - Mentally?
如果沃哥夫人的沉默和呆滞不是因为身体缘故……
If Mrs. Vogler's silence and immobility are her decision...
怎样?
Well?
那显示了她很强的精神力量
That shows great mental strength.
我可能应付不了
I might not be able to cope.
我猜你青定想看看日落
I thought that you might want to see the sunset.
要我打开收音机吗?
Shall I turn on the radio?
我想今晚有场歌剧
There is a play.
对不起,亲爱的
I'm sorry, my love.
噢,你得原谅我
Oh, you have to forgive me.
我什么都不要,但求你的原谅
I want nothing but your forgiveness.
原谅我,我能……
Forgive me and I can...
你在笑什么,沃哥夫人?这女演员很好笑吗?
What are you laughing at, Mrs. Vogler? Is the actress so funny?
你懂什么是宽恕吗?你知道什么?
What do you know about mercy? What do you know?
你知道什么是宽恕?
What do you know about mercy?
沃哥夫人,我不理解这些东西
Mrs. Vogler, I don't understand those things.
我对电影和戏剧很感兴趣,但我不经常去
I'm interested in film and theater, but I don't go very often.
我很欣赏艺术家
I have a tremendous admiration for artists.
我认为艺术对人们的生活是很重要的
I think that art is of enormous importance in people's lives,
尤其是对那些有困扰的人来说
especially for those who have problems.
我不应该对你讲这些的,沃哥夫人
I shouldn't talk about these things with you, Mrs. Vogler.
我是在履薄冰
I'm skating on thin ice.
看看有什么音乐没
Let's see if there's some music.
这个行吗?
Is that all right?
晚安,沃哥夫人,做个好梦!
Good night, then, Mrs. Vogler. Sleep well!
该死
Damn...
真滑稽
It's funny.
你可以随心所欲…
You can go about as you please...
做任何事
...do almost anything.
我要嫁给卡尔．亨利克,生几个孩子
I'll marry Karl-Henrik and have a couple of children,
都由我来养
which I'll have to raise.
一切都是注定的,在我内心里面
All of this is predestined. It's inside me.
没什么可担心的
It's nothing to think about.
这是一种很安全的感觉
It's a safe feeling.
我有一份喜欢的工作
I have a job that I like and enjoy.
足矣…
That's good, too...
但另一方面…
...but in another way.
也还不错
But it's good.
还行
Good.
搞不懂她到底是怎么回事
I wonder what's really wrong with her.
伊丽莎白．沃哥
Elisabet Vogler.
伊丽莎白
Elisabet.
在越南南部出现的骇人听闻的事情
整个广场刹那间聚集了许多人
今天刚好也是当地的重大节日
所有的警察很快就赶到现场
这是这里有史以来的第一桩事情
双方的斗争很激烈
其中有131人受伤
其中一名和尚自焚
火势很盛
警察没能把他抢救出来
此人自焚的真正目的还不明确
沃哥夫人,要我给你打开信吗?
Mrs. Vogler, would you like me to open the letter?
要我读给你听吗?
Shall I read it?
Shall I read it to you?
“亲爱的伊丽莎白
"Dearest Elisabet,
”因为他们不让我探望你,所以只能给你写信了
"Since I'm not allowed to see you, I'm writing to you.
“你也可以不看我的信,扔掉它
You don't have to read my letter. You can ignore it."
”我禁不住想用这种方式跟你联系
"I cannot help seeking contact with you this way.
“我被众多问题困扰着…
"I'm haunted by a constant question...
“我是不是在某些方面伤害了你?
"Have I hurt you in any way?
“是不是在不知不觉中伤害了你?
Have I unknowingly hurt you?"
“我们之间是不是有很大的误会?”
"Is there some terrible misunderstanding between us?"
你真的想让我再念下去吗?
Do you really want me to go on?
“就我所知现在我们还是幸福的
"I thought we were happy.
“我们从未如此亲近
We have never been so close."
“还记得你说过
"Do you remember saying,
“我开始知道婚姻意味着什么吗?
"'I'm beginning to understand what it means to be married'?
“你曾经告诉过我…
'You have taught me..."'
我看不清这个
I can't read it.
“你曾经告诉过我…
"'You have taught..."'
噢,知道了
Now I see.
“你曾经告诉过我,我们之间的交往
"'You have taught me that we have to see each other
“要像两个天真的孩子一样
"'as two anxious children,
“用善意和最好的动机
"'filled with good will and the best intentions,
“但…
but ru..."'
我知道了
Now I see.
“但却被我们只能部分控制的力量统治了
"'... ruled by powers that we can only partially control.'
“你还记得你曾经说过的这些吗?
Do you remember saying all that?"
“我们到森林里漫步
"We went for a walk in the woods,
“你停下来,抓着我外套的腰带
and you stopped and grabbed the belt of my coat."
信里面有张照片
There is a photo with the letter.
你儿子的照片,我不知道是否…
A photo of your son. I don't know if...
你要看吗,沃哥夫人?
Do you want it, Mrs. Vogler?
他看起来真可爱
He looks terribly cute.
伊丽莎白,我不知道
Elisabet, I don't think there's any point
你呆在这医院里有什么意义
in your staying at the hospital.
在这里你只会受到伤害
It's just hurting you to be here.
既然你不想回家,我建议你和艾玛护士
Since you don't want to go home, I suggest you and Sister Alma
去我海边的夏日小屋住段日子
stay at my summer house by the sea.
你以为我不明白吗?
Don't you think I understand?
无望的恶梦,不是表面上的,而是本质上的
The hopeless dream of being. Not seeming, but being.
每个梦醒时分都在时刻警惕
In every waking moment aware, alert.
两者之间的战争…别人怎么看你和你究竟是谁
The tug of war... what you are with others and who you really are.
一种眩晕的感觉
A feeling of vertigo
一种想被最终暴露的持久的渴望
and a constant hunger to be finally exposed.
希望被看透,被击倒…
To be seen through, cut down...
甚至被淹没
even obliterated.
每个欺骗的谚语,每个虚假的表情
Every tone of voice a lie. Every gesture false.
每次苦涩的微笑
Every smile a grimace.
自杀?
Commit suicide?
那是不可思议的
That's unthinkable.
你不会那样做
You don't do things like that.
但是你可以沉默和静坐
But you can refuse to move and be silent.
这样,你至少不用撒谎
Then, at least, you're not lying.
你可以把自己封闭起来,把世界关在门外
You can shut yourself in, shut out the world.
这样你无需扮演任何角色
Then you don't have to play any roles,
做任何虚伪的表情和手势
show any faces, make false gestures.
你是这么想的…
You'd think so...
但现实是残酷的
...but reality is diabolical.
你的藏身之所也并非是密不透风的
Your hiding-place isn't watertight.
到处都充斥着生活的骗局
Life trickles in everywhere.
你不得不做出反应
You're forced to react.
没人在乎
Nobody asks if it's real or not,
你是说实话还是撒谎
if you're honest or a liar.
那是只在剧院里才变得重要的事
That's only important at the theater,
或者甚至在那里也不是
perhaps not even there.
伊丽莎白,我懂你为何要沉默,为何不动弹
Elisabet, I understand why you're silent, why you don't move.
你的毫无生气已成定局
Your lifelessness has become a fantastic part.
我能理解,而且很钦佩
I understand and I admire you.
我想你该在这件事平静之后再扮演这个角色
I think you should play this part until it's done...
直到人们不再感兴趣
...until it's no longer interesting.
你便可摆脱了
Then you can leave it,
就像你摆脱其它角色一样
as you leave all your roles.
沃哥夫人和艾玛护士
Mrs. Vogler and Sister Alma
搬到了医生的夏日小屋
move into the doctor's summer house.
这位演员很喜欢这里的海滩
The seaside stay agrees very well with the actress.
漫步,钓鱼,烹饪,写信,娱乐
Her former apathy gives way to long walks, fishing,
使她先前的冷漠逐渐消逝
cooking, letter-writing, and other diversions.
艾玛护士也非常喜欢这里的乡村生活
Sister Alma enjoys the seclusion of the countryside
并且很细心的照顾着她的病人
and takes great care of her patient.
跟人比手会倒霉的
It's bad luck to compare hands.
伊丽莎白,我给你读一段书好吗?
Elisabet, can I read a bit of my book to you?
要是不打扰你的话?听听这个…
Or am I disturbing you? Listen to this...
“正如我们知道,自身固有的焦虑
"The anxiety we carry with us,
“我们所有破碎的梦,莫名的残忍
"all our broken dreams, the inexplicable cruelty,
“对死亡的恐惧
"the fear of death,
“以及对俗世痛苦深刻的洞察
the painful insight into our earthly condition..."
“已经破灭了我们超凡脱俗的希望
"...have worn out our hope of a divine salvation.
“我们内心抵抗黑暗和沉默的
"The cries of our faith and doubt
“信仰和疑虑的呼声
"against the darkness and the silence
“是我们孤独和恐惧
"are terrible proof
“最好的证明”
of our loneliness and fear."
你觉得是这样吗?
Do you think it's like that?
我不相信
I don't believe that.
想改变…但是我太懒了
To change... but I'm so lazy.
这让我很内疚
And it makes me feel guilty.
卡尔．亨利克经常指责我没有抱负
Karl-Henrik always scolds me for not having any ambitions.
他说我像具僵尸
He says I'm like a zombie.
我觉得这不公平
I think it's unfair.
我半业时是班上的好学生
I graduated with the highest marks in my class.
可能他说的是别的方面吧
Maybe he means something else.
你?
You?
抱歉
I'm sorry...
你知道…
You know...
在我毕业的那所医院
At the hospital, where I graduated,
有个专门给老护士住的地方
there is a home for old nurses,
那些一辈子都做护士的人…
ones who've been nurses all of their lives and lived for their work...
成天穿着白大褂…
always in uniform...
她们住在那里
and they live there.
想象一下一种能让你投入一生的强烈召唤…
Imagine having a calling that strong
that you devote your life to it...
相信一件事情并去做
Believing in something, doing something.
认为你的生命因之而有意义
To think your life has meaning.
我喜欢这样
I like that.
无论怎样都坚持下去
Sticking to it whatever happens.
这样你对别人来说是很重要的
I think you should be of importance to others.
你相信吗?
Do you believe that?
我知道这听起来很幼稚,但我相信这个
好大的雨!
What a downpour!
是的,他结婚了
Yes, he was married.
我们已经恋爱了五年
We had an affair for five years.
之后,他自然厌倦了
Then he got tired, of course.
我是如此的爱他,他是我的初恋
I was so in love, and he was the first.
就像一种持续的痛苦…
It was like a prolonged pain...
长期的隐痛,及短期的…
...long periods of pain and short moments of...
我想起这些都是因为你教我吸烟的缘故
I started thinking about it all because you've taught me to smoke.
他吸烟很厉害
He smoked a lot.
后来想想,这当然是很陈腐的,就像低级小说一样
In hindsight, it's banal, of course. Sort of like pulp fiction.
听起来很怪但我觉得一切好象虚幻
In a strange way, it was never real.
我不知道该怎么形容
I don't know how to describe it.
对他来讲我虚幻的
I was never real to him.
但可以青定的是我的痛苦是真实的
But my pain was real, that's for sure.
从某方面说,那是它的一部分,从某个令人呕心的方面
In some way, that was a part of it, in some nauseating way,
就像应该是这样的一样
as if it should be like that.
甚至我们对彼此所说的一切
Even the things we said to each other.
人们说我是一个很好的倾听者
People tell me that I'm a good listener.
很好笑是吧?
Isn't that strange?
从没有人倾听过我说话,像你这样
Nobody ever bothered to listen to me. Not the way you do now.
你倾听
You listen.
我想你是第一个听我说话的人
I think you're the first person to listen to me.
一定很无趣,你可以看你的书
It can't be interesting. You could read a book instead.
看着我,聊天,我希望这不会激怒你
Look at me, talking. I hope it doesn't irritate you.
聊天的感觉真好,是如此温暖和美妙
It feels so good to talk. It feels warm and nice.
以前从没有过这种感觉
I've never been in a mood like this before.
我一直都想有个姐妹,我只有哥哥
I've always wanted a sister. I only have brothers.
七个,很奇怪,是不是?然后我就出生了
Seven of them. Strange, eh? And then I turned up.
打从记事时起,就记得身边全是男孩
Boys have surrounded me all my life, as long as I can remember.
但我喜欢男孩
But I like boys.
但作为一个演员我想你一定了解
But you would know that with your experience as an actress.
我那么喜欢卡尔．亨利克,但是…
I like Karl-Henrik so much, but...
你或许只会爱一次
You probably only love once.
我对他那么忠诚
I'm faithful to him.
当然因为我的职业,我也没有不忠的机会
There are opportunities in my profession, you know.
卡尔．亨利克和我曾在海边租了一个小别墅
Karl-Henrik and I had rented a cottage by the sea once.
那是六月份,就我们两个
It was in June, and we were all alone.
有一天卡尔．亨利克去镇上了
One day Karl-Henrik had gone into town.
我一个人去了海滩
I went to the beach on my own.
那天天气晴朗暖和
It was a warm and nice day.
有个女孩躺在那儿
There was another girl there.
她从另一个岛来
She had come from another island
喜欢我们这海滩的光线充足和隐蔽
because our beach was sunnier and more secluded.
我们全裸着躺在那晒日光浴…
We lay there completely naked and sunbathed...
涂防晒霜,休憩
...dozing off and on, putting sunscreen on.
我们戴着廉价草帽
We had silly straw hats on.
我的上面缠有一条蓝色的丝巾
Mine had a blue ribbon.
我躺在那里…
I lay there...
看着周围的环境,享受大海和阳光
Iooking out at the landscape, at the sea and the sun.
确实很有趣
It was kind of funny.
突然我看到上面岩石上有两个身影
Suddenly I saw two figures on the rocks above us.
他们躲在背后时不时地偷看一下
They hid and peeped out occasionally.
我对那女孩说：“有两个男孩在偷看我们”
"Two boys are looking at us," I said to the girl.
那女孩叫卡特拉
Her name was Katarina.
“让他们看好了”,她说,并翻过身来
"Let them look," she said, and turned over on her back.
我当时感觉很滑稽
I had a funny feeling.
我想跳起来,穿好衣服
I wanted to jump up and put my suit on,
但我仍然俯卧在那里
but I just lay there on my stomach with my bottom in the air,
非常冷静,一点都不觉尴尬
unembarrassed, totally calm.
而且卡特拉就在我的旁边
And Katarina was next to me
大腿和乳房都露在外面
with her breasts and big thighs.
她只是不断的傻笑
She was just giggling.
我注意到男孩们正在向我们走近
I noticed that the boys were coming closer.
他们就站在那里看着我们
They just stood there looking at us.
我看出他们的怯懦
I noticed they were very young.
那个大胆点的开始接近我们…
The boldest one approached us...
并蹲在卡特拉的旁边
...and squatted down next to Katarina.
他假装是在扳他的脚趾
He pretended to be busy picking his toes.
我感觉非常奇怪
I felt very strange.
突然,卡特拉对他说
Suddenly Katarina said to him,
“嗨,你,怎么不过来?”
"Hey, you, why don't you come over here?"
然后她拉着他的手帮他把裤子和衬衫脱下来
Then she took his hand and helped him take off his jeans and shirt
突然他就骑到她的身上
Suddenly he was on top of her.
她指引着他,抓着他的屁股
She guided him in and held his butt.
另一个男孩就坐着看
The other boy just sat and watched.
我听到卡特拉笑着和那男孩耳语
I heard Katarina whisper in the boy's ear and laugh.
他的脸就对着我的脸
His face was right next to mine.
那是一张红彤彤的胖脸
It was red and swollen.
突然我转过去,对他们说
Suddenly I turned and said,
“能不能也到我这来?”
"Aren't you coming to me, too?"
卡特拉说：“去她那吧”
And Katarina said, "Go to her now."
他便从她身上下来
He pulled out of her and...
然后骑到我身上,很粗鲁
then fell on top of me, completely hard.
他抓着我的乳房
He grabbed my breast.
那很痛!
It hurt so much!
我很快便就被征服了,并马上兴奋起来
I was overwhelmed and came almost immediately.
你能相信吗?
Can you believe it?
我想告诉他小心点,别让我怀孕了…
I wanted to tell him to be careful not to make me pregnant...
他高潮来临时…
...when he came.
我有一种从未有过的体验…
I felt something I'd never felt in my life...
他把精液于射入我的体内
how his sperm was shooting inside me.
他抓着我的肩膀向后仰
He held my shoulders and bent backwards.
我来了一次又一次
I came over and over.
卡特拉躺在那里看着,从后面抱住他
Katarina lay there watching and held him from behind.
完事后,她就抱着他
After he came, she took him in her arms
用他的手来自慰
and used his hand to make herself come.
快到高潮时,她就叫得像个女妖
When she came, she screamed like a banshee.
我们三个都开始笑
The three of us started laughing.
我们又叫了那个还在斜坡上的男孩
We called to the other boy, who was sitting on the slope.
他叫彼得
His name was Peter.
他在阳光下颤抖而且看起来挺不解
He seemed confused and was shivering there in the sunshine.
卡特拉开了他的裤子和他玩
Katarina unbuttoned his pants and started to play with him.
他快射时,她就把它放在她嘴里
And when he came, she took him in her mouth.
他弯下身去,吻她的背
He bent down and kissed her back.
她转过身去,用双手抱住他的头
She turned around, took his head in both hands,
把她的乳房给他
and gave him her breast.
另一个男孩非常兴奋,我们又开始了
The other boy got so excited that he and I started all over again.
还和前一次一样美妙
It was just as nice as before.
然后我们一起游泳,之后就分道扬镳了
Then we had a swim and went our separate ways.
回到家时,卡尔．亨利克已经从镇上回来了
When I came home, Karl-Henrik was already back from town.
我们共进晚餐并喝了点红酒
We had dinner and some red wine.
然后我们开始做爱
Then we had sex.
感觉从未没那么好过,以前或后来
It had never been that good, before or after.
你能理解吗?
Can you understand that?
当然我怀孕了
And I got pregnant, of course.
卡尔．亨利克是一个医生
Karl-Henrik, studying to be a doctor,
带我去一个同事那里堕了胎
took me to a colleague who carried out the abortion.
我们无所谓因为我们不想要孩子
We were both pleased. We didn't want to have children.
总之,那时候不想要
Not then, anyway.
这太没意义了
It doesn't make any sense.
这不对
None of it fits together.
为些小事而内疚
You feel guilty for little things.
你能理解吗?
Can you understand that?
你下决心会做的一切事情
And what happens to everything that you make up your mind to do?
都有必要做吗?
Is it necessary to do it all?
有可能同时成为另一个人吗?
Is it possible to be one and the same person
我是说两个人…
at the same time? I mean, two people?
噢,上帝,真是无聊
Oh, Lord, it's so silly.
根本就没有理由去哭
No reason to start crying.
我去拿块手帕
I'll get a handkerchief.
天快亮了
It's almost morning.
还在下雨
And it's still raining.
想象一下,不停的讲
Imagine, talking incessantly.
我一直在讲,你一直在听,你一定很烦
I've been talking and you've been listening. How boring for you.
我的生活有什么值得你感兴趣吗?
What could possibly interest you about my life?
我应该像你一样
I should be like you.
你知道那晚我看了你的电影之后有什么想法吗?
You know what I thought after seeing your movie that night?
回家对着镜子,我想
When I came home and looked in the mirror, I thought,
“我们很相像”
"But we look alike."
别误会我,你是如此完美
Don't misunderstand me. You're more beautiful.
但在某些方面…我想如果我努力的话,可以变得和你一样
But somehow... I think I could change myself into you if I tried.
我是说,内在的
I mean, inside.
你也可以成为我,就这样
You could be me, just like that.
但你的灵魂太深邃,那样你会吃不消的
But your soul would be too big. It would stick out everywhere!
去睡吧,否则,会在桌上睡着的
Go to bed. Otherwise, you'll fall asleep at the table.
我得去睡了,否则我会在桌上睡着的
I have to go to bed now or I'll fall asleep at the table.
那样肯定不舒服
That would be uncomfortable.
晚安
Good night.
伊丽莎白
Elisabet.
昨晚你和我讲话了吗?
Did you speak to me last night?
你到过我房间吗?
Were you in my room?
要我给你带信吗?
Shall I take your mail, too?
亲爱的,我想永远这样生活下去
My dear, I could live like this forever.
沉默,过隐居的生活,无欲无求
Silent, living a secluded life, reducing my needs,
感觉我破碎的心灵终于开始愈合了
feeling my battered soul finally starting to smooth itself out.
艾玛在照顾我,用最令人感动的方式宠爱我
Alma takes care of me, spoils me in the most touching way.
我相信她很喜欢这样而且很喜欢我…
I believe that she likes it here and that she's very fond of me...
或许是用一种无意识的迷惑的方式在爱我
perhaps even in love in an unaware and enchanting way.
无论如何,研究她是一件很有趣的事情
In any case, it's very interesting studying her.
有时她为过去的罪孽哭泣
Sometimes she cries over past sins...
和陌生男孩的纵情以及随后的堕胎
an orgy with a strange boy and a subsequent abortion.
她声称自己的感觉
She claims that her perceptions
和行为是不一致的
do not correspond with her actions.
你在看剧本
You're reading a play.
这是很健康的迹象,我会告诉医生的
That's a healthy sign. I'll tell the doctor.
你觉得我们是不是很快就要走了?
Do you think we'll leave soon?
我有点想念城市了,你呢?
I'm starting to miss the city. Aren't you?
你想让我真正幸福吗?
Would you like to make me really happy?
我知道这对你是一种牺牲,但现在我需要你的帮助
I know it's a sacrifice, but right now I could use your help.
不用冒什么险
Nothing dangerous.
我只是想让你跟我聊聊
I just want you to talk to me.
没什么特别的
Nothing special.
我们什么都可以谈…比如说晚餐吃什么
We could talk about anything... what to have for dinner,
你是否觉得雨后水会有点冷
if you think the water is cold after the rain,
不适合游泳
if it's too cold to go swimming.
就聊一会儿,一分钟
Just talk for a few minutes. One minute.
你也可以大声朗读,只要你说句话就可以了
You could read aloud, just say a couple of words.
我在尽量控制,你还是保持沉默
I have to try not to get angry. You remain silent.
那是你的特权,但现在我需要你跟我说话
That's your prerogative, but now I need you to talk to me.
亲爱的,求求你,难道你一句话也不能说吗?
Dearest, please, can't you just say one word?
我知道你会拒绝
I knew you would refuse.
你根本不知道我的感受
You can't know how I feel.
我以为伟大的艺术家,对人类有最大的怜悯…
I thought that great artists had great compassion for people...
他们的创作来源于对自身深刻的怜悯
...that they created through a great compassion
和需求
and a need to help.
那真蠢
That was stupid.
你利用了我,出于不可告人的原因
You have used me. For what, I don't know.
现在你不再需要我了,便抛弃我
Now that you don't need me anymore, you throw me away.
噢,是的,我知道这是无稽之谈…
Oh, yes, I hear how false it sounds...
“但你确实是利用我然后抛弃我”
"You used me and then you threw me away."
仅此而已,每句话,甚至这混账眼镜都在利用我!
That's how it is, every word. And then these glasses!
你伤害了我
You've hurt me badly.
还在背后嘲笑我
You've laughed at me behind my back.
是的,我看了你写给医生的信
Yes, I read the letter that you wrote to the doctor.
是的,我看了,因为没有封口,我全部看了
Yes, I did, because it wasn't sealed, and I read all of it.
你让我说话
You made me talk.
你让我透露没向任何人说过的秘密
You made me talk about things I've never told anybody.
而你,做了个成功实验,是吧?
And you told. What a study, eh?
你,你…
You, you...
你说话啊!
You're going to talk!
如果你想说的话,该死的…
If you have something to say, goddamn it...
不要!
No, don't do it!
怕了,是吧?
That scared you, didn't it?
刹那间,你真的怕了,是不是?
For a second, you were really scared, right?
那种怕死的感觉,是不是?
A real fear of death, huh?
“艾玛疯了”,你想
"Alma has gone crazy," you thought.
你到底是怎样一种人?
What kind of a person are you?
或许你在想：“我会记住这张脸
Or maybe you thought, "I'll remember that face,
用这种音调,这种语气”
that tone of voice, that expression."
我会给你些你永远无法忘怀的记忆!
I'm going to give you something you won't forget!
你在嘲笑,对吗?
You're laughing, are you?
这对我来说没那么简单
It's not that simple for me.
也不那么有趣
Not so funny, either.
但你总是有好笑的事
But you have always your laughter.
难道必须这样吗?
Does it have to be like this?
别撒谎,跟我说实话
Is it really important that you don't lie, that you tell the truth
用一种真实的语气,聊天就那么难吗?
talk with a genuine tone of voice?
除开谎言,托词
Can you live without talking freely?
和漠然,你就不会别的交谈方式吗?
Lie and make excuses?
找懒惰和厌倦的理由来敷衍自己?
Isn't it better to give yourself permission to be lazy and lie?
或许你展现真我会感觉好些
Perhaps you get better if you just be the way you are.
不,你不明白
No, you don't understand.
你理解不了我所说的
You don't understand what I'm saying.
你是不可接近的
You're unapproachable.
医生说你很健康,但我很奇怪你的疯狂
The doctor said you're healthy, but I wonder about your madness.
你所表现的一切让所有人信服
You're acting healthy so well that everyone believes you.
除了我,因我知道你的堕落
Everyone but me, because I know how rotten you are.
瞧我都做了些什么
Look at me behaving like this.
伊丽莎白!
Elisabet!
伊丽莎白,请原谅我
Elisabet, forgive me.
噢,上帝,我真的像个白痴
Oh, my God, I behaved like an idiot.
我是来帮助你的,看我把这弄成什么样了
I don't know what came over me. I'm here to help you.
都是那该死的信
It was that awful letter.
那让我太失望了
I was so disappointed.
你让我谈谈我自己
You asked me to talk about myself.
我感觉很好,而且你看起来很善解人意
It felt so good. You seemed so kind and understanding.
我喝了点酒,聊天的感觉太好了
I had been drinking. It felt so good to talk about it all.
我得意忘形了,像您这样伟大的演员会听我说话
I was flattered that a great actress like you bothered to listen.
同时我想那或许对你也有益处
Somehow I thought it would be nice if it was of some use to you.
但那真蠢,纯粹的自我裸露
But it is so awful. It's sheer exhibitionism.
伊丽莎白,希望你…希望你能原谅我
Elisabet, I want you to... I want you to forgive me.
我这么在乎你,你对我来说真的很重要
I care for you so much. You mean so much to me.
我从你身上学到很多东西,我们不要像敌人一样反目
I've learned so much from you. Let's not part as enemies.
你不愿意原谅我,是因为你太骄傲了
You don't want to forgive me because you're too proud!
你不屈服,是因为你认为没这个必要
You don't want to give in because you don't think it's necessary.
我不会…我不会…
I won't... I won't...
不说话,也不听,不能理解…
...doesn't speak, doesn't listen, can't understand...
伊丽莎白!
Elisabet!
这意味着…不能…用来收听?
What means... can't use... to make listen?
事实上…
Practically...
你睡着的时候,你的脸很放松…
When you sleep, your face is relaxed...
嘴巴张开着,很丑陋
...your mouth is swollen and ugly.
你额头上有一些细小皱纹
There's a mean wrinkle on your forehead.
充满了眼泪和睡眠的气息
You smell of sleep and tears.
我能看见你脖子上的脉搏
I can see the pulse on your neck.
还有你经常用化妆品掩饰起来的伤疤
It has a scar you normally cover with makeup.
伊丽莎白
Elisabet!
他又在叫了
He's calling again.
我去看看他到底想干什么…
I'll find out what he wants from us...
在这么远的我们独居的房子的外面
...out here, far away here in our solitude.
伊丽莎…
Elisa...
抱歉,我吓着你了
I'm sorry if I frightened you.
我不是伊丽莎白
I'm not Elisabet.
我没有什么需求
I have no demands.
我也不想打扰你,你以为我不知道吗?
I didn't want to disturb you. Don't you think I understand?
医生把一切都告诉我了
The doctor has explained things.
但很难向你的小儿子解释
But it's hard to explain to your little boy.
我尽量吧
I do the best I can.
有一种很深刻的、难以抓住的东西…
There's something deep down, difficult to get a grip on.
你爱某个人,或者说你…
You love somebody, or say you do...
这是很切实的,像言语一样
...it's tangible, like words.
沃哥先生,我不是你妻子
Mr. Vogler, I'm not your wife.
她也爱你,你们形成了一种结合
You are also loved. You form a bond.
那给你安全,一种保持活力的机会,是不是?
It gives you security, a chance to endure, doesn't it?
没有迷失自己,我怎么能全部说出来?
How can I say it all without losing myself?
而且不让你心烦?
Without boring you?
我像以前一样爱你
I love you as much as ever.
不,别担心,亲爱的
No. Don't worry, my love.
我们彼此拥有,我们彼此信任
We have each other. We trust each other.
我们知道彼此的想法,我们互相爱着对方
We know each other's thoughts. We love each other.
是这样的,对不对?
That's how it is. Isn't it?
重要的是我们的努力,而非所取得的成绩,对吗?
More important is the effort. Not what we accomplish, right?
互相看待对方
To see each other as children,
就像是无助的孤独的痛苦的孩子一样
tormented and helpless, lonely children.
告诉你的儿子,他妈妈很快就会回来…
Tell your little boy that his mother will be back soon...
妈妈病了,但她很想她的儿子
...that Mommy has been ill, but she longs for her little boy.
记得给他买一个小玩具
Remember to buy a toy for him.
告诉他是妈妈送的礼物,别忘了
Tell him it's a present from Mommy. Don't forget.
我对你感到如此的亲切
I have such a great tenderness for you.
几乎快忍不住了
It's almost unbearable.
我不知道该怎么来处理这种感觉
I don't know what to do with my tenderness.
我是靠你的亲切而活的
I live on your tenderness.
伊丽莎白,和我在一起好吗?你感觉好吗?
Elisabet, is it good for you with me? Is it nice for you?
你知道,你是一个很不错的情人
You're a wonderful lover. You know that.
我亲爱的!
My dearest!
给我镇定剂,把我扔掉
Give me a sedative, throw me away.
不,我不能再继续下去了…
亲爱的…
No, I can't go on anymore...
放开我!一切太羞耻了
My darling...
Leave me alone! It's shameful, all of it.
放开我!
Leave me alone!
我这么冷漠,这么堕落,这么无关紧要
I'm cold and rotten and indifferent.
所有一切都是谎言和冒充
It's all lies and imitation.
这是什么?
What have you got there?
你手里藏了什么?
What are you hiding under your hand?
让我看看
Let me see.
是你小儿子的照片,你撕掉的那张
It's the picture of your little boy, the one you tore up.
我们得谈谈
We have to talk about it.
告诉我,伊丽莎白
Tell me now, Elisabet.
那么我说
Well, then, I will.
是那晚的舞会,对吧?
It was an evening at a party, wasn't it?
夜深而嘈杂
It was late and rather noisy.
开始的时候,有人对你说…
In the early hours, someone said to you...
“伊丽莎白,你有艺术家和女人所具有的一切
"Elisabet, you have everything as a woman and as an artist,
但没有慈母心.”
but you lack motherliness."
你嘲笑是因为你觉得很荒唐…
You laughed because you thought it was ridiculous...
但你还是忍不住要想他所说的话
...but you couldn't stop thinking about what he had said.
你越想越担心…
You grew more worried...
因此你要求丈夫让你怀孕
...so you let your husband make you pregnant.
你想当一个母亲
You wanted to be a mother.
但你发现已经成了定局时,你开始感到害怕
When you knew it was definite, you became afraid,
害怕负责,害怕被束缚
afraid of responsibility, afraid of being tied down,
害怕离开剧院…
afraid to leave the theater...
害怕痛苦,害怕死亡
...afraid of pain, afraid of dying,
害怕你日趋膨胀的身体
afraid of your swelling body.
但每时每刻
But all the time you acted,
你都装成是一个很幸福的母亲
played the part of the happy expectant mother.
每个人都说：“她从没这么漂亮过.”
And everybody said, "She has never been this beautiful."
你几次试着打掉胎儿
You tried several times to get rid of the fetus.
但是都失败了
But you failed.
当你意识到已经无可挽回时,你开始憎恨这个小孩
When you knew it was inevitable, you started to hate the child
希望是个死胎
and wished it would be stillborn.
你希望那个小孩是死的
You wished that the baby would be dead.
你想要一个死了的小孩
You wanted a dead child.
那是一个长时间也很痛苦的分娩
It was a long and difficult delivery.
你痛了好些天
You suffered for days.
孩子是用镊子取出来的
The baby was delivered with forceps.
你厌恶的看着你哭叫的孩子
You looked with disgust at your screaming child
悄悄地说：“你能不能早点死?能不能早点死?”
and whispered, "Can't you die soon? Can't you die?"
但他活下来了
But he survived.
小孩一天到晚的哭叫
The boy screamed day and night...
你很讨厌他
...and you hated him.
你很害怕,你感到愧疚
You were afraid. You felt guilty.
最后,亲戚和奶妈照看这个小孩
In the end, relatives and a nanny took care of the boy,
你离开病床重返剧院
and you could leave your sickbed and return to the theater.
但痛苦并没有结束
But the suffering wasn't over.
而这个小孩对却对他的母亲如此眷恋
The boy was seized by a massive and
unfathomable love for his mother.
你拼命的抵抗
You resisted desperately
因为承受不起这爱
because you felt that you could not return it.
你不断的尝试再尝试…
You try and try...
但你每次和他的见面都是如此冷酷、尴尬
...but the meetings with him are cruel and awkward.
你做不到
You can't do it.
你冷漠,漠不关心
You're cold and indifferent.
他看着你
And he looks at you.
他爱你,而且他很脆弱
He loves you, and he's soft,
因为他死缠你不放,你甚至想揍他一顿
and you want to hit him for not leaving you alone.
你觉得他很讨厌,厚嘴唇,丑陋的身躯
You think he's repulsive, with his thick lips and ugly body
合泪的祈求的眼睛
and his moist and pleading eyes.
你认为他很讨厌,你很害怕
You think he's repulsive, and you're afraid.
你手里藏了什么?
What are you hiding under your hand?
让我看看
Let me see.
是你的小儿子的照片,你撕掉的那张
It's the picture of your little boy, the one you tore up.
我们得谈谈
We have to talk about it.
告诉我,伊丽莎白
Tell me now, Elisabet.
那么,我来说吧
Well, then, I will.
那是在一个舞会的晚上,是不是?
It was an evening at a party, wasn't it?
夜深而且很嘈杂
It was late and rather noisy.
开始的时候有人对你说…
In the early hours, someone said to you...
“伊丽莎白,你有艺术家和女人所具有的一切
"Elisabet, you have everything as a woman and as an artist..."
但你没有慈母心.”
"...but you lack motherliness."
你笑了因为你觉得很荒唐…
You laughed because you thought it was ridiculous...
但你还是忍不住要想他所说的话
...but you couldn't stop thinking about what he had said.
你越想越担心…
You grew more worried...
因此你要求丈夫让你怀孕
...so you let your husband make you pregnant.
你想当一个母亲
You wanted to be a mother.
但你发现已经成了定局时,你开始感到害怕
When you knew it was definite, you became afraid...
害怕负责,害怕被束缚
...afraid of responsibility, afraid of being tied down,
害怕离开剧院…
afraid to leave the theater...
害怕痛苦,害怕死亡
...afraid of pain, afraid of dying,
害怕你日趋膨胀的身体
afraid of your swelling body.
但每时每刻
But all the time you acted,
你都装成是一个很幸福的母亲
played the part of the happy expectant mother.
每个人都说：“她从没这么漂亮过.”
And everybody said, "She has never been this beautiful."
你几次想打掉这个小孩
You tried several times to get rid of the fetus.
但都失败了
But you failed.
当你知道一切都无可挽回时
When you knew it was inevitable...
你开始憎恨这个小孩
...you started to hate the child...
希望是个死胎
...and wished it would be stillborn.
你希望这个小孩是死的
You wished that the baby would be dead.
你想要一个死了的小孩
You wanted a dead child.
那是一个长时间也很痛苦的分娩
It was a long and difficult delivery.
你痛苦了好些天
You suffered for days.
孩子是用镊子取出来的
The baby was delivered with forceps.
你厌恶的看着你哭叫的孩子
You looked with disgust at your screaming child
悄悄地说：“你能不能早点死?
and whispered, "Can't you die soon?
能不能早点死?”
Can't you die?"
小孩一天到晚的哭叫
The boy screamed day and night,
你很讨厌他
and you hated him.
你很害怕,你感到内疚
You were afraid. You felt guilty.
最后,亲戚和奶妈照看这个小孩
In the end, relatives and a nanny took care of the boy...
你离开病床重返剧院
...and you could leave your sickbed and return to the theater.
但痛苦并没有结束
But the suffering was not over.
而这个小孩对却对他的母亲如此眷恋
The boy was seized by a massive and
unfathomable love for his mother.
你拼命的抵抗
You resisted desperately
因为承受不起这爱
because you felt that you could not return it.
你不断的尝试再尝试…
You try and try...
但你每次和他的见面都是如此冷酷、尴尬
...but the meetings with him are cruel and awkward.
你做不到
You can't do it.
你冷漠．漠不关心
You're cold and indifferent.
他看着你
And he looks at you.
他爱你,而且他很脆弱
He loves you, and he's soft,
因为他死缠你不放,你甚至想揍他一顿
and you want to hit him for not leaving you alone.
你觉得他很讨厌,厚嘴唇,丑陋的身躯
You think he's repulsive, with his thick lips and ugly body
合泪的祈求的眼睛
and his moist and pleading eyes.
你认为他很讨厌,你很害怕
You think he's repulsive, and you're afraid.
不
No.
我不是你,我的感觉和你不一样
I'm not like you. I don't feel the same as you.
我是艾玛护士,我到此是来帮你的
I'm Sister Alma. I'm only here to help you.
我不是伊丽莎白．沃哥
I'm not Elisabet Vogler.
你才是伊丽莎白．沃哥
You're Elisabet Vogler.
我想要…
I would like to have...
我喜欢…
I love...
我没有…
I haven't...
我学过很多
I've learned quite a lot.
我们瞧瞧我能维持多久
Let's see how long I can hold out.
我永远都不会像你,我一直在改变
I'll never be like you. I change all the time.
你可以做你想做的事,不要打扰我
You can do what you want. You won't get to me.
什么都不用说…对着光做检查
Say nothing... cut a candle.
不是现在,不,不
Not now. No, no.
永恒的警告,无法预料的…
Warning and timeless. Unforeseen...
如果注定要发生．而没有,那么…失败
When it had to happen, it didn't, so... failure.
你呆在那里,应该是我
You stand there, but I should be.
不要插嘴,不要靠近…
Not inward, not close...
集中精力劝告其他人
Say collect and advise others.
绝望的,或许…
Desperate, maybe...
我接受…是的,但最近的…
I take... yes, but what is the closest...
叫什么?不
What is it called? No...
我们,我们,我,我…
Us, we, me, I...
许多厌恶的言词
Many words and disgust,
无法忍受的痛苦,恶心
unbearable pain, the nausea.
试着听我说
Try to listen to me.
跟着我念
Repeat after me...
没什么
Nothing.
不,没什么
No, nothing.
没什么
Nothing.
好的
There.
是的
That's right.
就应该这样
That's how it should be.
剧终  谢谢观赏 字幕由 Wendy's PaPa 重新调校时间轴